Register of the Aleksandr Aleksandrovich Kurenkov (A. A. Koor) Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Aleksandrovich Kurenkov papers
1892-1992
2001C84
Hoover Institution Archives
(1.2 linear feet) 8 microfilm reels
Correspondence, speeches and writings, personal documents, printed matter, and memorabilia, relating to Russian émigré affairs, and to aspects of the early history of Russia.
Kurenkov, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich, 1891-1971
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
A. A. Kurenkov was born in Kazan' on 13 May 1891. He studied at Kazan' Military School and began military service in the fortress at Auschwitz. During the First World War he was gassed and wounded. Thereafter he specialized in defense against gas attacks, and was promoted to command the 1st Chemical Company of the XLIV Corps with the rank of captain (1917). Demobilized in 1918, Kurenkov joined an officers' unit in Shadrinsk during the anti-Bolshevik uprisings in Siberia and the Urals in summer 1918, rising to command the 27th Verkhoturskii Siberian Rifles in 1919.
Kurenkov arrived in Seattle, Washington, in February 1923, where he later abbreviated his name to Koor. Here he became involved in numerous émigré organizations, particularly those with a monarchist flavor, and he was promoted to the rank of major general by Grand Duke Vladimir Kirillovich in 1937. In San Francisco, where he moved in the 1950s, Kurenkov edited and published a monarchist newspaper called Vestnik pravdy (1964-1968). In 1947, he received the degree of "Doctor of Psychology" from the "College of Divine Metaphysics, Indianapolis, Indiana." Following this, he became intensely interested in ancient Russian and Slavic history, writing about and promoting the so-called "Vles-Kniga," a written work purporting to date from the 5th-6th centuries, A.D., dismissed as a forgery by all competent scholars. Much of the collection consists of his musings and collected materials on this subject.
Chronology
1891 May 13 Born, Kazan', Russia
? Studied in Kazan' University, Russia
1914?-1917 Served in the Imperial Russian Army
1918-1921 Participated in the Civil War
1923 Emigrated to the United States
1925-1927 Served in the National Guard of Washington State
1937 May 11 Promoted to the rank of Major-General by Kirill Vladimirovich, Grand Duke of Russia
1947 Graduated with the degree of Doctor of Psychology from the College of Divine Metaphysics, Indianapolis, Indiana
1951 October 12 Member, Les Chevaliers de la Croix de Lorraine et Compagnons de la Résistance
1971 Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
Aleksandr Aleksandrovich Kurenkov (also known as Alexander A. Koor/Koorenkoff), was a Russian Major-General. After immigrating to the United States in 1923 he became an active member of different Russian émigré associations and the émigré monarchist movement. He expressed his views in the newspaper Vestnik pravdy (San Francisco) for which he was a publisher and editor (see OVERSIZE FILE). This collection mainly contains Koorenkov's writings, as well as background materials and printed matter, related to his interest in the pre-history of Russia and the Slavs, and in particular, the so-called "Vlesova Kniga" or "Doshchechki Izenbeka."
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia. Armiia--Officers; Russia--History.; Russians--United States.
- Biographical File, 1947-1951 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Bibliography, clipping, service records, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1941-1968 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by the name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1937-1956 and undated (Box 1)
  Magazine and newspaper articles, letters to the editor, and speech, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1892-1979 (Box 2-5)
  Appeals, books, brochures, bulletins, charter, clippings, correspondence, flyers, magazines, minutes of meetings, translations, arranged alphabetically by heading
- Oversize File, 1947-1968 (Box 6)
  Clippings, diplomas and issues of the newspaper Vestnik pravdy
- Photographs, 1937 and undated (Box 6)
  One print depicting Kirill Vladimirovich, Grand Duke of Russia, and a copy of a print depicting A. A. Kurenkov with IU. P. Miroliubov
- Printed Matter, 1923-1992 (Box 7-8)
  Books, brochures, clippings, magazines, newspapers, offprints. Not microfilmed
- Memorabilia, 1919(?)
  Banner with commemorative embroidery, "Otdel'nomu batal'onu imeni kapitana Kurenkova ot Solikamska i uezda." On display in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. Not microfilmed
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1947-1951 (Box 1)
  General note
  See also SUBJECT FILE/Russian Veteran's Society of the World War, Inc.
  - Bibliography (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clipping about Kurenkov, 1951 (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes related correspondence
  - Diplomas, 1947-1951
    See OVERSIZE FILE/Diplomas
  - Service records (Folder 1: 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1941-1968
  See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS for editorial correspondence and SUBJECT FILE/ Committee of the United Russian-American National Organizations of the Pacific N.W. States
  - Elshin, Aleksandr Iakovlevich, 1949-1950 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Ivitskii (Ivitzky), Georgii Dionis'evich, 1949-1952 (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes clipping about Ivitskii
  - Lenkov, A., n.d. (Folder 1: 6)
  - Merger, K. A., 1968 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Otdel Rossiiskogo Anti-kommunisticheskogo Tsentra v N'iu Iorke na Tikhookeanskom poberezh'i SShA, 1952 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Samoilov, E., 1956-1965 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Savin (?), P. P., 1966 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Slobodchikov, Nikolai Aleksandrovich, 1954 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Tsygal'skii (Tzigalsky?), Aleksandr Viktorovich, 1941 (Folder 1: 12)
    Includes an obituary
  - Vitkovskii, Vladimir Konstantinovich, 1951 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Wilson, Oliver, 1951
    See BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Clipping about Kurenkov
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1937-1956 and undated
  For Kurenkov's editorials written specifically for Vestnik pravdy, see OVERSIZE FILE/Issues of the newspaper Vestnik pravdy
  - General (Folder 1: 14)
  - "Otvet na 'Otvet A. A. Kuru',", n.d. (Folder 1: 15)
    Holograph. Includes materials by others
  - "Akademik Oleg Ivanovich Iadov,", n.d. (Folder 1: 16)
    Printed copy
  - "Dom Romanovykh," Zhar-ptitsa, n.d. (Folder 1: 17)
  - "Doshchki,", n.d. (Folder 1: 18)
    Typescript of two different versions
  - "'Dve povesti vremennykh liet' i dve raznykh istorii russkago naroda,", n.d. (Folder 1: 19)
    Typescript
  - "Kak nado byt' dobrym i pochemu,", n.d. (Folder 1: 20)
  - "Las tablas de Izenbek," Oriente europeo, n.d. (Folder 1: 21)
  - "Slaviane,", n.d. (Folder 1: 22)
  - "Svastika,", n.d. (Folder 1: 23)
  - Untitled work on the history of Russia, n.d. (Folder 1: 24)
    Typescripts of two different versions. Includes attachments
  - "V zashchitu Rossii: Pis'ma russkikh anti-kommunistov mestnym amerikanskim gazetam" (with Vladimir K. Kit), n.d. (Folder 1: 25)
  - Untitled letter to the editor, Russkii listok, about Russian veterans of World War I, 1937 (Folder 1: 26)
  - "Otkrytoe pis'mo g. Aleksandru Nikolaevu," Novaia zaria, 1949 January (Folder 1: 27)
    Typescript and printed copy. Includes materials by others
  - "Otkrytoe pis'mo ko vsem Ierarkham i Iereiam pravoslavnoi tserkvi vsekh iurisdiktsii Soedinennykh Shtatov," Novaia zaria, 1949 March 19 (Folder 1: 28)
    Printed copy. Includes materials by others
  - "Po povodu soobshcheniia iz Manily: 'Imperatorskii polkovnik'...," Novaia zaria, 1949 June 17 (Folder 1: 29)
  - "Kto predal Admirala Kolchaka,"., 1949 July(?) (Folder 1: 30)
    Typescripts of two different versions. Includes materials by others
  - "O chude Izraelia g. G. I. Iasinitskago,"., 1951 (Folder 1: 31)
    Typescript. Includes materials by others
  - "Russky pismeny," speech, Museum of Russian Culture, 1952 August 10 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Collection of articles published in Zhar-ptitsa, 1952 October - 1956 November (Folder 1: 33)
    Printed copies. Original order by Kurenkov retained. Includes typescripts of some articles
  - "Rus' i normanskaia teoriia," Russkaia zhizn', 1953 September 5 (Folder 1: 34)
  - "Doshchechki: O gotakh," Zhar-ptitsa, 1954 December (Folder 1: 35)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1892-1979 (Box 2)
  - Committee of the United Russian-American National Organizations of the Pacific N.W. States, Seattle, Washington. (Folder 2: 1)
    Correspondence, membership list, minutes of meetings
  - Elshin, Aleksandr Iakovlevich. (Folder 2: 2-13)
    Includes correspondence and documents relating to the Fond pomoshchi L. F. Krasnovoi (Lady L. F. Krasnoff's Welfare Society), 1926-1949
  - Law--Philosophy. E. N. Trubetskoi, Istoriia filosofii prava, 1892-1893 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Miroliubov, Iuri Petrovich. (Folder 2: 15)
    Letters related to the search of "Doshchechki Izenbeka" in Brussels, 1944
  - Monarchy--Russia. (Folder 2: 16-20)
    Brochures, bulletins, correspondence, clippings, magazines, and other printed matter related to the émigré monarchist movement
  - Monarchy--Russia (Box-folder 3: 1-19)
  - Monarchy--Russia (Box-folder 4: 1-10)
  - Romanov, House of. (Folder 4: 11-13)
    See also PHOTOGRAPHS.
    Appeals, clippings, flyers and other printed matter
  - Russia--History. Grigorii Ianushevskii, Otkuda proiskhodit slavianskoe plemia Rus' with attachments,; and Marzheret (Jacques Margeret), Sostoianie Rossiiskoi Derzhavy i Velikago Kniazhestva Moskovskogo v 1606 godu, 1928-1930(?) 1913 (Folder 4: 14-15)
  - Russian Veteran's Society of the World War, Inc., Seattle, Washington (Obshchestvo russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny). (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
    Correspondence, minutes of meetings, 1926-1952
  - Russians--United States (Folder 5: 3-5)
  - Russkoe monarkhicheskoe ob"edinenie zagranitsei, 1922(?) (Folder 5: 6)
    Charter
  - Vlesova Kniga. (Folder 5: 7-17)
    See also OVERSIZE FILE/Subject file/Vlesova Kniga.
    Includes background materials and translations by Kurenkov and printed matter related to Kurenkov's interest in Vlesova Kniga and the origins of the Slavs, often with his notes on the margins
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1947-1968 (Box 6)
  - Diplomas, 1947-1951 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Issues of the newspaper Vestnik pravdy, for which Kurenkov was a publisher and editor, #1 - # 50, and two issues of the magazine Vestnik pravdy, #1 and #2., (1964 May 4) (1968, April?) (1967 December 25-1968 January 7) (1968 June 28) (Folder 6: 2)
    Some issues contain his editorials
  - Subject file - Vlesova Kniga (Folder 6: 3)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1937 and undated (Folder 6: 4)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1923-1992 (Box 7-8)
  Not microfilmed.
  Books, brochures, clippings, magazines, offprints, sometimes with Kurenkov's notes on the margins
- MEMORABILIA, 1818-1919
  Banner with commemorative embroidery, "Otdel'nomu batal'onu imeni kapitana Kurenkova ot Solikamska i uezda." On display in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco